Nelson E. Díaz-Díaz

☎+57-314-236-7334

LP 255

⊠nelson.diaz@saber.uis.edu.co

Bucaramanga, Colombia, Cra 27 calle 9, 680002

Bio: Received the B. Sc. and M. Sc. degrees in Computer Science from the Universidad Industrial de Santander, Colombia, in 2012 and 2015, respectively, and Ph. D. degrees in Electronic Engineering from the Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia in 2020, sponsored by a 727 Colciencias scholarship. Currently, he holds a Postdoctoral position with the Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso (PUCV), Santiago, Chile, under the supervision of Prof. Esteban Vera. His research interests include high-dimensional signal processing, sparse image representation, adaptive sensing, compressive video, and spectral image classification. Please click on the bold text to access to my academic web page and my CvLAC. **Academic WebPage:**, CvLAC: Investigador Junior

SKILLS

- Languages: Spanish (Native), English (B2), French (B2)
- Programming: Python (NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib), MATLAB
- Document Creation: Office tools, LATEX

PROFESSIONAL EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy in Engineering: emphasis in electronic

2016-2020

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Santander, Colombia

GPA: 4.55/5.00

Advisor: PhD. Henry Arguello

Doctoral thesis: "Coded Aperture Design for Adaptive Compressive Spectral Imaging"

Master of Science in Computer Science

2013-2015

Department of Computer Science

Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia.

GPA: 4.72/5.00

Advisor: Ph.D. Henry Arguello.

Master thesis: "High-dynamic range compressive spectral imaging by adaptive filtering"

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

2006-2012

Department of Computer Science

Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia.

GPA: 3.88/5.00

Advisor: Ph.D. Lola Xiomara.

Graduate project:: "Immune algorithm to solve job shop scheduling".

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Associate - School of Electrical Engineering

August 2020 - Present

Project: Shuffled Rolling Shutter for Snapshot Temporal Imaging -Improved

compressive temporal imaging using a shuffled rolling shutter

Role: Main researcher

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaiso, Chile Valparaiso, Chile

Assistant Professor Data Structures, Fundamentals of programming, February 2020 - July 2020 Technology of the Information and Communication TIC

Department of Computer Science

Universidad de Investigación y Desarrollo, Bucaramanga, Colombia

Research Intern on Ultrasound Imaging TéSA, Telecommunications for Space an Aeronautics Project: Convolutional Sparse Coding for Motion Estimation of Ultrasound Imaging	Fall-winter 2018-2019
Role: Main researcher Toulouse, France	
Assistant Professor Digital image processing Department of Electrical Engineering Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia	2016-2017
Research Intern on Adaptive Grayscale Coded Aperture Design Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering University of Texas A&M, College Station, TX, USA	Summer 2015
Adjunct Researcher on Computational Optical Image Processing High-dimensional signal processing research group (HDSP) Department of Computer Science Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia	2013-Present
Research Assistant on Operation Research Research Group in Biomedical Engineering Department of Computer Science Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia	2011-2012
HONORS AND AWARDS	
Meritorious doctoral thesis Meritorious degree work Universidad Industrial de Santander Bucaramanga, Colombia	March 10th, 2020
Colciencias Scholarship Scholarship to pursue Ph.D. studies in Colombia. Francisco Jose de Caldas Institute for the Development of Science and Technolog Colciencias, Bogota D.C., Colombia	2016 - 2019 gy
STUDENT CO-SUPERVISION	
Diego Armando Pinzon Bachelor of Science in Computer Science Universidad Industrial de Santander, Bucaramanga, Colombia	2012 - 2013
JOURNAL REVIEWER	
Optics Express Optica (Formerly Optical Society of America), USA	2019 - Present
Applied Optics Optica (Formerly Optical Society of America), USA	2019 - Present
Journal of Electronic Imaging (JEI) The International Society for Optics and Photonics, SPIE	2021 - Present
Journal of Selected Topics in Signal Processing (J-STSP) Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, IEEE	2021 - Present
Transactions on Computational Imaging (TCI) Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, IEEE	2022 - Present

ACADEMIC COLLABORATIONS

Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso, (Valparaíso, Chile)

2020 - Present

Collaboration with Dr. Esteban Vera

Project: Snapshot video sensing with application in space surveillance and satellite

instrumentation Role: Main researcher

Other activities: Joint development of grants and application to The National Fund for Scientific and Technological Development, FONDECYT (Chile), and Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso (PUCV) Valparaíso, Chile.

Universidad Industrial de Santander, (Bucaramanga, Colombia)

2013 - Present

Collaboration with Dr. Henry Arguello

Project: Adaptive grayscale coded aperture design

Role: Master and PhD student

Other activities: Joint development of grants and application to the Colombian Institute of Development of Science and Technology - Colciencias

PROJECTS WITH COLOMBIAN RESEARCH GROUPS

Universidad de Investigación Y Desarrollo, (Bucaramanga, Colombia)

2020 - present

Project: Procesamiento de nube de puntos adquiridas con un escáner laser terrestre mediante técnicas de aprendizaje de máquina (machine learning) (2021)

Project: Arquitectura óptica de imágenes espectrales comprimidas para clasificación en agricultura usando deep learning (2020)

Role: Main researcher

Other activities: master's and undergraduate's project evaluator.

JOURNAL PAPERS

- Nelson Diaz, Alejandro Alvarado, Pablo Meza, Felipe Guzman, and Esteban Vera. Multispectral Filter Array Design by Optimal Sphere Packing. 11 2022 DOI:https://doi.org/10.36227/techrxiv.21502899.v1
- 2. Esteban Vera, Felipe Guzmán, and Nelson Díaz. Shuffled rolling shutter for snapshot temporal imaging. *Opt. Express*, 30(2):887–901, Jan 2022 DOI: 10.1364/OE.444864
- 3. Nelson Diaz, Omar Gallo, Jhon Caceres, and Hernan Porras. Real-time ground filtering algorithm of cloud points acquired using terrestrial laser scanner (tls). *International Journal of Applied Earth Observation and Geoinformation*, 105:102629, 2021 DOI:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jag.2021.102629
- 4. N. Diaz, J. M. Ramirez, E. Vera, and H. Arguello. Adaptive classification via spatial contextual information in multisensor compressive spectral imaging. *IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*, 14:9254–9266, 2021 DOI:10.1109/JSTARS.2021.3111508
- Nelson Diaz, Carlos Hinojosa, and Henry Arguello. Adaptive grayscale compressive spectral imaging using optimal blue noise coding patterns. *Optics & Laser Technology*, 117:147–157, September 2019 DOI:https://doi.org/10.1016/j.optlastec.2019.03.038
- Nelson Diaz, Hoover Rueda, and Henry Arguello. Adaptive filter design via a gradient thresholding algorithm for compressive spectral imaging. *Applied Optics*, 57(17):4890–4900, June 2018 DOI:https://doi.org/10.1364/AO.57.004890
- Edson Flórez, Nelson Díaz, Wilfredo Gómez, Lola Bautista, and Darío Delgado. Evaluación de algoritmos bioinspirados para la solución del problema de planificación de trabajos. I+ D Revista de Investigaciones, 11(1):133–143, 2018 Open access
- 8. Nelson Diaz, Hoover Rueda Chacon, and Henry Arguello Fuentes. High-dynamic range compressive spectral imaging by grayscale coded aperture adaptive filtering. *Ingeniería e Investigación*, 35(3):53–60, 2015 DOI:http://dx.doi.org/10.15446/ing.investig.v35n3.49868

CONFERENCE PAPERS

- 1. Alejandro Alvarado, Nelson Díaz, Pablo Meza, Felipe Guzmán, and Esteban Vera. Multispectral mosaic design using a sphere packing filter array. In *Imaging and Applied Optics Congress* 2022 (3D, AOA, COSI, ISA, pcAOP), page CTh4C.1. Optica Publishing Group, 2022
- 2. Felipe Guzmán, Nelson Díaz, and Esteban Vera. Improved compressive temporal imaging using a shuffled rolling shutter. In *OSA Optical Sensors and Sensing Congress 2021 (AIS, FTS, HISE, SEN-SORS, ES)*, page JTh6A.9. Optical Society of America, 2021
- 3. J. Bacca, N. Diaz, and H. Arguello. Compressive classification via deep learning using single-pixel measurements. In 2020 Data Compression Conference (DCC), pages 359–359, 2020
- 4. N. Diaz, C. Noriega-Wandurraga, A. Basarab, J.Y Tourneret, and H Arguello. Adaptive coded aperture design by motion estimation using convolutional sparse coding in compressive spectral video sensing. In 2019 IEEE 8th International Workshop on Computational Advances in Multi-Sensor Adaptive Processing (CAMSAP), Guadeloupe, France, pages 1–5, Dec 2019
- N. Diaz, A. Basarab, J.Y. Tourneret, and H. Arguello. Cardiac motion estimation using convolutional sparse coding. In 2019 27th European Signal Processing Conference (EUSIPCO), Coruña, España, Sep 2019
- 6. M. Marquez, N. Diaz, J. Bacca, S. Pertuz, and H. Arguello. Compressive light field spectral imaging in a single-sensor device by using coded apertures. In *Imaging and Applied Optics 2017 (3D, AIO, COSI, IS, MATH, pcAOP)*, page CTh1B.5. Optical Society of America, 2017
- N. Diaz, J. Bacca, and H. Arguello. Gradient thresholding algorithm for adaptive colored coded aperture design in compressive spectral imaging. In *Imaging and Applied Optics 2017 (3D, AIO, COSI, IS, MATH, pcAOP), San Francisco, California*, page JTu5A.4. Optical Society of America, 2017
- 8. Nelson Diaz, Hoover Rueda, and Henry Arguello. Adaptive uniform grayscale coded aperture design for high dynamic range compressive spectral imaging. In *Hyperspectral Imaging Sensors: Innovative Applications and Sensor Standards, Baltimore, USA*, volume 9860, page 98600A. International Society for Optics and Photonics, 2016
- 9. N. Diaz, H. Rueda, and H. Arguello. High-dynamic range compressive spectral imaging by adaptive filtering. In 2015 3rd International Workshop on Compressed Sensing Theory and its Applications to Radar, Sonar and Remote Sensing (CoSeRa), pages 89–93, June 2015

MEMBERSHIPS

- IEEE Signal Processing Society, Member
- Optica (Formerly Optical Society of America), Member

ACADEMIC REFERENCES

- PhD Hoover Fabian Rueda, Postdoctoral Associate, Boston University, hfarueda@gmail.com
- PhD Henry Arguello Fuentes, professor Universidad Industrial de Santander, Colombia, henarfu@uis.edu.co
- PhD Estevan Vera, professor Pontificia Universidad Catolica de Valparaiso, Chile, esteban.vera@pucv.cl